Museum District Records, 1976-2013
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Museum District Records 1976-2013
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 421
12.8 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Robert Orlowski, 2010
Historical Information
The Museum District Association, also known as the West of the Boulevard Civic Association (hereafter referred to as MDA or WOBCA) was founded in 1964 to protect and advance the interests of the community. Their mission is also to realize the potential of the neighborhood so as to improve the quality of life for the residents living therein. The museum district is considered to be the areas up to but not including the south side of W. Broad Street on the north, Interstate I-195 on the west, the alley north of W. Cary Street on the south, and both sides of Boulevard from Broad Street to Idlewood Avenue on the east, within the boundaries of the City of Richmond, Virginia.
The MDA is presided over by a Board of Directors numbering between 12 and 18 individuals. There are standing committees overseeing all zoning and land use within the district, as well as committees for public safety and crime prevention, traffic control and environmental needs such as sidewalk conditions and garbage removal. According to the by-laws of the association any resident, be they leasing or owning, over the age of eighteen can become a voting member.
The neighborhood became designated as a federal and state historic district in 1993. The first Mother's Day House and Garden Tour held in 1995. The Columns, the MDA newsletter is delivered to all residents in the neighborhood quarterly. Their website, www.museumdistrict.org has an overview of the history of the museum district.
Scope and Content
The collection is comprised of institutional materials ranging from the 1970s to 2009 for the MDA. There are financial records, board meeting minutes and agendas, and correspondence that are generated from the daily running of the association. There is also a great deal of presidents' notes, MDA published materials and their various stages before publishing, and miscellaneous administration documents. Most zoning cases are residential with a few restaurant business included, and are primarily comprised of board member emails and member emails pertaining to each zoning case.
Arrangement
This collection was donated in phases. The first donation given in neatly bound and labeled binders and has been placed chronologically but otherwise remains within each binder in complete original order. The materials donated at later times deal almost entirely with correspondence and zoning issues and are separated by materials dated before 2001, when the West of the Boulevard Civic Association became officially known as the Museum District Association, and materials dated after 2001 generated by the Zoning and Land Use Committee (Z and LUC). Materials from this portion of the MDA are organized alphabetically, with the exception of correspondences and reports which are placed chronologically in the original order they were donated. Licensing and zoning cases are arranged alphabetically by the address under review.
There are five series in this collection. Series 1. is the WOBCA papers dealing with zoning issues and board reports and correspondence from 1976 to 2001. The second is the administration information and correspondence contained within the binders and date from 1986 to 2002. Series 3 contain the Z and LUC case files. The fourth series is object based and is comprised of profile silhouette patterned fabric from a MDA event as well as miscellaneous papers. Lastly is the oversize materials; including blueprints for properties requiring zoning approval and news clippings relating to the neighborhood.
SERIES: 1. West of the Boulevard Civic Association, 1976-2001 2. Administration, 1986-2002 3. MDA Zoning and Land Use Committee, 2000-2009 Subseries A. Cases and Licensing Cases, 1994-2009 4. Fabric and Miscellaneous, circa late 1990s 5. Oversize, 1976-2009
Contents List
- West of the Boulevard Civic Association, 1976-2001 (Box 1)
  - WOBCA Zoning Issues, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - WOBCA Zoning Issues, 1982 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - WOBCA Zoning Issues 1983 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - WOBCA Zoning Issues, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 1994 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 1995 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 1996 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 1997 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - WOBCA Board of Directors, 1997 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - WOBCA Z and LUC, 1997 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 1998 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 1999 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 2000 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - WOBCA Correspondence, Agenda, and Meetings, 2001 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Correspondence of Joseph Yates, President of the WOBCA, undated (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Correspondence of Joseph Yates, President of the WOBCA, circa 1998 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Design Overlay District Background and Design Guidelines, 1996 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Design Overlay District Draft Proposal, 1995 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Draft of the Urban Design District Proposal, circa 1995 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Historic West of the Boulevard Civic Association Newsletter, circa 1996 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - How to research your historic house, 1993 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Maps and Facts, undated (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Near West Planning District, 1983 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Records, copies, 1917, 1935 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Records 1971, 1991 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Sidewalks and Alleys Ordinances, undated (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Special Use Ordinance for 716 N. Boulevard, 1984 March 4 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Special Use Ordinance for 3103 Ellwood, 1985 March 1 and 2001 January 22 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Zoning for 2911 Grove Ave, 1986 December 31 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Zoning for 3511-3521 Park Ave, 1987, August 20 and 1987 September 24 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Zoning for 2910 Patterson Ave, 7-Eleven, 2000 March 2 (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Zoning for 3500 Patterson Ave, 1986 December 10 (Box-folder 1:32)
- Administration, 1986-2002 (Box 1A-4)
  - Membership Meetings, Board Lists and Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1A:2)
  - General Information 1990 (Box-folder 1A:3)
  - Board Minutes, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 1A:4)
  - Correspondence and Minutes, 1992 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - President's Notebook, 1994 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - President's Notebook, 1994 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Colonial Downs Off-Track Betting Case, President Notes and Letters, and the WOBCA Mother's Day House and Garden Tour, 1995 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Membership Lists, Year's Schedule of Activity, Correspondence, 1996 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Minutes and Information, 1998 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Financial Records, 1998 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - President's Notebook, 1999 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - President's Notebook, 1999 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Financial Records, 1999 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Correspondence, Board Agendas and Notes, and Miscellaneous, 1999 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Financial Records, 2000 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Financial Records, 2001 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Financial Records, 2002 (Box-folder 4:6)
- Zoning and Land Use Committee Cases and Licensing, 2000-2009 (Box 5-7)
  - Agendas, circa 2008 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Animal Care and Control Facility Transfer, 2006 January 5 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Article XII Definitions, undated (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Board Meetings, 2009 September 9 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Board of Zoning Appeals, BZA, 2009 November 04 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Boulevard and Monument Street Lights, circa 2008 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Charitable Gaming Commission, circa 2008 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Citizen's Guide to Neighborhood Improvement, 2004 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - City Codes, undated (Box-folder 5:9)
  - City Council Meeting, 2006 June 26 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - City Council Rules of Procedure, 2007 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - City Ordinance and Resolutions, undated (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Commission of Architectural Review (CAR) Meeting, 2006 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Correspondence pertaining to the Traffic Study at Boulevard and Main, circa 2008 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Correspondence with West Grace Street Association (WGSA), concerning 2317 W. Grace St. circa 2000 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Council of the City of Richmond Meeting, 2006 January 9 (Folder 5:16)
  - Current Council Districts and Zoning Charters, 2000 (Box-folder 5:17)
  - Maps, undated (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Mission of the Z and LUC, undated (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Motion to Amend Ordinance No. 2007-227, 2007 (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Old Historic Neighborhood of Springhill requesting help, 2008 (Box-folder 5:21)
  - Ordinance No. 2009-236 (Noise), 2009 (Box-folder 5:22)
  - Parking Division 3, Residential Restrictions, 2006 (Box-folder 5:23)
  - Parking Meeting, 2006 December (Box-folder 5:24)
  - Parking Meeting, 2008 (Box-folder 5:25)
  - Parking Special Exemption Amendment Proposal, 2007 (Box-folder 5:26)
  - Property Maintenance and Incentive Programs, undated (Box-folder 5:27)
  - Restricted Parking Ordinance, 2004 (Box-folder 5:28)
  - Richmond Old and Historic District Handbook, undated (Box-folder 5:29)
  - Sign to the Museum District, 2005 October 31 (Box-folder 5:30)
  - Tree Removal on Monument Ave, 2006 (Box-folder 5:31)
  - VCU Urban and Regional Planning student Ronnie Clements West of Broad Revitalization Project, 2007 (Box-folder 5:32)
  - Correspondence, Board Agendas and Notes, 2002 (Box-folder 5:33)
  - Correspondence, Board Agendas and Notes, 2005 (Box-folder 5:34)
  - Board of Zoning Appeals Cases, 2006 (Box-folder 5:35)
  - Correspondence, Board Agendas and Notes, 2006 (Box-folder 5:36)
  - Report to the Board, 2006 (Box-folder 5:37)
  - Correspondence, Board Agendas and Notes, 2007 (Box-folder 5:38)
  - Board Correspondence, 2007 January-July (Box-folder 5:39)
  - Board Correspondence, 2007 August-December (Box-folder 5:40)
  - Correspondence, Board Agendas and Notes, 2008 (Box-folder 5:41)
  - Reports and Correspondence, 2008 February (Box-folder 5:42)
  - Correspondence, 2008 March-May (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Corresopndence, 2008 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Corresopndence, 2008 July 31-September 4 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Correspondence, 2008 September (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Correspondence, Board Agendas and Notes, 2009 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Zoning Laws and Court Cases, 2005 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Zoning and Licensing Cases, 1994-2009 (Box 6-7)
    - ABC License Review, Park Ave Grill- Surfish and Raw Bar, 1999 May - 2000 August (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Bangles and Beads, Xtra's Cafe, Crenshaw Street Parking Deck Hours, 2008 October (Box-folder 6:8)
    - 1 N. Belmont, Stuzzi, 2010 (Box-folder 6:9)
    - 25-27 N. Belmont, Belmont Food Shop, undated (Box-folder 6:10)
    - 201 N. Belmont, Zues Gallery Cafe, 2006 (Box-folder 6:11)
    - 2900-2908 W. Broad St., 1991 October 3 (Box-folder 6:12)
    - 3301 W. Broad, WTVR Channel 6, 2007 (Box-folder 6:13)
    - Boulevard and Hanover, VMFA Curb Cut and Parking Deck, 2009 (Box-folder 6:14)
    - 118 S. Boulevard, 2007 June 25 (Box-folder 6:15)
    - 428 N. Boulevard, Virginia Historical Society, 2000 January 11 (Box-folder 6:16)
    - 3114 W. Cary, Second Debut Goodwill, 2007 August - October (Box-folder 6:17)
    - 3123 W. Cary, Weezies, 2007 (Box-folder 6:18)
    - 3312 W. Cary, Veterinary Emergency Center, 2004 (Box-folder 6:19)
    - 3322 W. Cary, 2008 (Box-folder 6:20)
    - 800 N. Cleveland, Hot Spot, 2001 (Box-folder 6:21)
    - 801 N. Cleveland, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 6:22)
    - 801 N. Cleveland, Corner Cafe, 2002 (Box-folder 6:23)
    - 20 S. Colonial, 2009 October-November (Box-folder 6:24)
    - 107 S. Colonial, formerly the Cube, 2008 (Box-folder 6:25)
    - 109 N. Crenshaw, 2008 April 24 (Box-folder 6:26)
    - 3015 Cutshaw, The Marquee, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 6:27)
    - 3300-3332 Cutshaw, 2007 December 3 (Box-folder 6:28)
    - 3404 Ellwood, 2007 January-February (Box-folder 6:29)
    - 3101 Ellwood, Parking Requirements for UB PO-2, 2009 May- October (Box-folder 6:30)
    - 3101 Ellwood, 2001 and 2006 (Box-folder 6:31)
    - 3152 Ellwood, 2009 August-September (Box-folder 6:32)
    - 3225 Ellwood, 2006 April (Box-folder 6:33)
    - Floyd, Ellwood, Belmont and Auburn Alley Way Building Plans, David Johannes, 2009 (Box-folder 6:34)
    - 3101 W. Franklin, Maury Place, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 6:35)
    - 3101 W. Franklin, Maury Place Supporting Materials, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 6:36)
    - 3109 W. Franklin, 2008 (Box-folder 6:37)
    - 3324 W. Franklin, 2009 (Box-folder 6:38)
    - 2238 W. Franklin, 2004 May-June (Box-folder 6:39)
    - 2811 Grove Ave, 2002, 2004, 2007 (Box-folder 6:40)
    - 3143 Grove Ave, 2009 October (Box-folder 6:41)
    - 3149 Grove Ave, 2009 May (Box-folder 6:42)
    - 3217 Grove Ave and 111 N. Dooley, 2004 October 22 (Box-folder 6:43)
    - 3232 Grove Ave, fencing, 2008 (Box-folder 6:44)
    - 3536 Grove Ave, Chiropractor's Office Sign, 2008 (Box-folder 6:45)
    - 2926 Kensington, 2009 March 10 (Box-folder 7:1)
    - 3101 Kensington, Lee School Lofts, circa 2002 (Box-folder 7:2)
    - 3500-3501 Kensington, Kensington Place, 2006-2007, 2009 (Box-folder 7:3)
    - 2901 Monument, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 7:4)
    - 3003-3005 Monument, 2006 (Box-folder 7:5 and 6)
    - 3123 Monument, Lord Fairfax Apartments, 1998 April 11 (Box-folder 7:7)
    - 3224 Monument, 2007 January (Box-folder 7:8)
    - 3307 1/2 Monument, Garage Demo, 2006-2008 (Box-folder 7:9)
    - 10 N. Nansemond, Cary Place, 2010 (Box-folder 7:10 and 11)
    - 1618 Park, Fan District Association Case, 2007 November-December (Box-folder 7:12)
    - 2920-2922 Park, Caliente 2006 (Box-folder 7:13 and 14)
    - 3400 Park, undated (Box-folder 7:15)
    - 3519 Park, 2009 July-October (Box-folder 7:16)
    - 3121 Patterson, 2008 April 14 (Box-folder 7:17)
    - 3129 Patterson, 2006 January-February (Box-folder 7:18)
    - 210 N. Sheppard, undated (Box-folder 7:19)
    - 600 N. Sheppard, Cafe Diem, 2001 September 01 (Box-folder 7:20)
    - 600 N. Sheppard, Fat Albert s, 1982, April-June (Box-folder 7:21)
    - 610 N. Sheppard, Oaxaca, 2006 May-June (Box-folder 7:22)
    - 3301 Stuart, 2009-2010 (Box-folder 7:23)
    - 3304 Stuart, 2008 (Box-folder 7:24-30)
    - 3417 1/2 Stuart, 2009 April-May (Box-folder 7:31)
    - Tilden Alley, St. Gertrude s School Parking, 2008 July (Box-folder 7:32)
    - VMFA Satellite Parking Instructions for Splendors of Egypt,1999 June 1-30 (Box-folder 7:33)
- Fabric, circa late 1990s (Box 8)
  - Fabric Silhouettes circa late 1990s (Box-folder 8:1)
- Oversize, 1976-2009 (Box 9)
  - Oversize news clippings, blueprints, miscellaneous 1976-2009 (Box-folder 9:1)